We've been asked to address the theme of changing conversations.
طُلب منا مراعاة موضوع تغير المحادثات.
that's a really important point to be at.
من الهام مراعاة هذه النقطة.
From the discourses that are going on within architecture
بناء على الجدل القائم في مجال الهندسة المعمارية
as well as throughout society,
وكذلك في المجتمع،
I think it is time to change the way that we look at things.
أظن أنه قد حان الوقت لنغير نظرتنا للأشياء.
As an architect, I've been involved with architectural projects,
وكمعماري، عملت بمشاريع معمارية،
with urban planning projects,
ومشاريع التخطيط الحضري،
and more recently, projects that engage much more with the landscape.
ومؤخرًا، في مشاريع ترتبط كثيرًا بالمشهد المحيط.
Now I can see so many opportunities
يمكنني الآن رؤية الكثير من الفرص
and so many ways in which design can contribute
والطرق حيث يمكن للتصميم المشاركة
and has the capacity to effect social change.
والتأثير على التغيير الاجتماعي.
And that's what I'm going to talk to you today about.
وهذا هو ما سأحدثكم عنه اليوم.
Starting off, I think it might be useful to talk a little bit about architecture,
بداية، أعتقد أنه من المفيد أن أتحدث قليلًا عن الهندسة المعمارية،
because I think for many people,
لأني أظن أن الكثير من الناس
architecture is a slightly mystical activity.
يرون الهندسة المعمارية كنشاط غامض.
Not many people know what architects do.
ولا يعلم كثيرون ما يفعله المعماريون.
A lot of the time, I'm not sure the architects know what they're doing.
وأغلب الوقت، لا أعلم إن كان المعماريون يعلمون ما يفعلونه.
But we try,
ولكننا نحاول،
and it's important to try and embrace that
ومن المهم أن نحاول ونتقبل ذلك
and try and understand what that means.
ونحاول أن نفهم ما يعنيه ذلك.
When I talk about architecture today, I'm not talking about the profession.
عندما أتحدث عن الهندسة المعمارية اليوم، فإني لست أتحدث عن المهنة.
I'm not talking about an activity that's pursued by a select group of people
ولا أتحدث عن نشاط تسعى إليه مجموعة محددة من الأشخاص
with some specialized knowledge.
الذين يملكون معرفة خاصة.
I'm talking about architecture in the bigger sense:
ولكني أتحدث عن الهندسة المعمارية بشكل أعمق:
architecture in terms of the room that we're in,
الهندسة المعمارية من حيث المكان الذي نشغله،
architecture as a pervasive activity,
والهندسة المعمارية كنشاط واسع الانتشار،
architecture as the activity that is the creation of shelter,
والهندسة المعمارية كنشاط لصنع المأوى،
the creation of space,
وصنع الحيز،
the design and the creation of spaces between buildings,
وتصميم وخلق المساحات بين البنايات،
the landscape.
والمشاهد المحيطة.
It's man's interaction with the landscape.
إنها تفاعل الإنسان مع محيطه.
Our construction of the built environment --
إنشاؤنا للبيئة المبنية...
that's what I mean by architecture.
وهذا هو ما أعنيه بالهندسة المعمارية.
It's not a specialized thing.
وليس شيئًا متخصصًا.
And over the last, I suppose, 20 or 30 years,
وكما أفترض، على مدى 20 أو 30 سنة الماضية،
with the predominance of the internet
مع هيمنة الإنترنت
and the wonderful and exciting advancements
والتقدم المذهل والمثير
that are taking place in technology,
الحادث في مجال التكنولوجيا،
one of the things that has happened is that our perception of the world
فإنه من بين الأمور التي حدثت، أن تصورنا للعالم
has become commodified.
أصبح يدور في إطار السلع.
It's become reduced in many ways
لقد تضاءل بطرق عدة
to a perception that is two-dimensional.
ليصبح تصورًا مسطحًا.
We spend a lot of our time, a lot of our lives,
نحن نمضي أكثر وقتنا ومعظم حياتنا،
looking at the world through screens,
في النظر إلى العالم من خلال الشاشات،
whether it's our laptops or television screens
سواء كانت حواسيبنا المحمولة أو شاشات التلفاز،
or monitors at airports or in the workplace
أو الشاشات في المطارات أو في مكان العمل،
or even our telephones are now screens.
وحتى هواتفنا أصبحت الآن بشاشات.
And it has this effect of reducing our perception of the world.
وكان لذلك هذا الأثر في الحد من تصورنا للعالم.
It expands it in many ways, but it can reduce it,
إنه ينميه بطرق عدة، ولكن يمكنه أن يحده،
it can turn into icons our idea or our notion of certain concepts
فيمكنه أن يحول أفكارنا ورأينا عن بعض المفاهيم إلى رموز
or ideas that are, in fact, maybe a lot more pervasive
أو في الواقع، إلى أفكار أكثر انتشارًا
than the two-dimensional image can convey.
مما يمكن أن تنقله هذه الصورة المسطحة.
And I think that's true about architecture.
وأظن أن هذا ينطبق على الهندسة المعمارية.
I think we've grown accustomed to thinking about architecture
أعتقد أننا اعتدنا على التفكير في الهندسة المعمارية
in a really primarily two-dimensional way, in a flat way,
بطريقة ثنائية الأبعاد بشكل أساسي، بطريقة مسطحة،
that the building is about what it looks like, how it appears,
أن المبنى يدور حول مظهره والشكل الذي يبدو عليه،
it's visual commodity.
إنه سلعة بصرية.
But it's much more than that.
ولكنه أكثر من ذلك.
It's much more than an aesthetic or just a sensory experience.
إنه أكثر من مجرد تجربة جمالية أو حسية.
That's very important,
وهذا هام للغاية،
but it's much more than that.
ولكنه أكثر من ذلك.
It's a complex operation.
إنه عملية معقدة.
And a big part of architecture and a big part of design
وجزء كبير من العمارة والتصميم
involves understanding the context in which that design exists
يعتمد على فهم السياق الذي يوجد فيه هذا التصميم
or in which it's going to exist.
أو الذي سيتواجد فيه.
It's having the imagination to try and predict or project
إنه امتلاك الخيال لمحاولة التنبؤ أو تصور
where the building or where the urban space
مكان المبنى أو المساحة الحضرية
or where the landscape is going to be located,
أو المحيط الذي سيتواجد فيه،
how it's going to be used,
وكيف سيتم استغلاله،
what are the operations, what are the activities
وما هي العمليات والأنشطة
that are going to take place in that space.
التي ستحدث في هذا الحيز.
And you might call those the programmatic aspects of architecture,
ويمكن تسمية ذلك بالجوانب البرمجية للهندسة المعمارية،
the programmatic aspects of design.
الجوانب البرمجية للتصميم.
And I think that in recent times, we've tended to privilege
وأعتقد أننا في العصر الحديث، أصبحنا نميل إلى تمييز
or put at a higher level
أو الرفع من شأن
that visual sensory perception or desire about architecture
هذا التصور أو الرغبة الحسية البصرية في الهندسة المعمارية،
ahead and in advance of those programmatic needs.
أكثر من هذه الحاجات البرمجية.
We've tended to kind of create monuments, create icons
فأصبحنا نميل إلى إنشاء النصب التذكارية، وصنع الرموز
that create a sensation or create effect,
التي تترك انطباعًا أو أثرًا،
without really thinking through the value of the operation
بدون التفكير بجدية في قيمة العملية
that those places or those spaces can affect.
التي يمكن أن تؤثر عليها هذه الأماكن والفراغات.
And it's in that zone or in that area that I think we need to start looking
وفي هذا النطاق أو المساحة، أعتقد أن علينا النظر
or trying to understand
أو البدء بفهم
how architecture or how design can really impact on society,
كيفية تأثير الهندسة المعمارية والتصميم على المجتمع،
and how it can address some of the problems
وكيف يمكن أن تعالج بعض المشكلات
that we're facing.
التي نواجهها.
The big buzzword in design and in what I do
الكلمة الطنانة في التصميم وفي ما أقوم به،
and I think what everybody does
وفي ما يفعله الجميع على ما أعتقد،
is the idea of sustainability.
هي فكرة الاستدامة.
Sustainability is an idea, a notion or a concept
والاستدامة هي فكرة أو نظرية أو مفهوم
that's triangulated by three very important concepts or ideas:
يقع ضمن ثلاثة مفاهيم أو أفكار هامة للغاية وهي:
the environment, the economy and society.
البيئة والاقتصاد والمجتمع.
Well, the global economy seems to be currently in a kind of meltdown situation.
يبدو أن الاقتصاد العالمي في حالة انصهار حاليًا.
A lot of work needs to be done there.
وينبغي أن نبذل المزيد من الجهد هناك.
The environment that we live in is challenged.
البيئة التي نحيا فيها تواجه تحد.
We've got global warming, we've got rising tides,
فلدينا الاحتباس الحراري، وارتفاع المد والجزر،
we've got all sorts of disasters taking place,
وكل أنواع الكوارث التي تقع،
all sorts of things happening
وجميع الأحداث
that threaten the equilibrium of the world and the environment that we live in.
التي تهدد توازن العالم والبيئة التي نعيش فيها.
And society itself is also challenged and threatened
والمجتمع نفسه يواجه تحد وتهديدًا
by some of the issues that we're faced with.
بسبب بعض القضايا التي نواجهها.
I think we've heard about some of those issues today
وأظن أننا قد سمعنا عن بعض هذه القضايا اليوم،
and the need to change the paradigm in which we perceive those things.
وضرورة تغيير النموذج الذي نتصور من خلاله هذه الأشياء.
It's really very crucial that we do that.
إنه أمر بالغ الأهمية حقًا أن نفعل ذلك.
So how does design impact that?
إذن، كيف يؤثر التصميم على ذلك؟
How can how can I, as a designer, or anybody as a designer
كيف يمكنني كمصمم، أو يمكن لأي شخص كمصمم
or any architect
أو لأي مهندس معماري
or how can society --
أو كيف يمكن للمجتمع...
in what way can design impact on that,
وبأي طريقة يمكن أن يؤثر التصميم على ذلك،
in what way can it affect that?
كيف يمكنه التأثير على ذلك؟
I'm going to talk today
سوف أتحدث اليوم
about ways in which I think design can impact on society,
عن الطرق التي يمكن أن يؤثر بها التصميم على المجتمع،
very specifically on society,
وتحديدًا على المجتمع،
and how that idea of design can infiltrate the idea of society
وكيف يمكن أن تتغلغل فكرة التصميم في فكرة المجتمع
and work with society in the operations of society
وتعمل مع المجتمع في عمليات المجتمع
in this programmatic way
بهذه الطريقة البرمجية
to effect social change.
للتأثير على التغيير الاجتماعي.
This is an image of Frederick Street in the early part of the last century.
هذه صورة لشارع (فريدريك) في أوائل القرن الماضي.
And I think it's a good image in lots of ways.
وأعتقد أنها صورة جيدة بعدة طرق.
It seems like that little triangulation of the environment,
يبدو أن مثلث البيئة
the economy and society
والاقتصاد والمجتمع
seems to be in a kind of balance.
في نوع من التوازن.
So it seems that in cities we can see that balance
لذلك يبدو أنه يمكننا رؤية هذا التوازن في المدن،
that cities are symbols or ciphers
وأن المدن هي الرموز أو الشفرة
or ways in which we can we can understand the confluence of those forces.
أو الطرق التي تمكننا من فهم تأثير هذه القوى.
And through time,
ومع مرور الوقت،
there have been times when cities have done that very successfully.
كان هناك مدن فعلت ذلك بنجاح تام.
There are lots of examples of very good cities
هناك أمثلة كثيرة لمدن جيدة جدًا
which have found themselves at a specific moment in time
وجدت نفسها في وقت ما
at a point of balance or equilibrium.
في نقطة تعادل أو توازن.
If we look at Port of Spain as a city,
إذا نظرنا إلى مدينة مثل (بورت أوف سبين)،
and we consider the idea that, once upon a time,
وأخذنا بالاعتبار أنه في يوم ما
Port of Spain was just a little cluster,
كانت (بورت أوف سبين) مجرد تجمع صغير،
a little fishing village at the mouth of the St. Ann's River.
قرية صيد صغيرة عند مصب نهر (سانت آن).
And yet it's grown to be such a big, complex conglomeration,
ومع ذلك نمت لتصبح كتلة بهذا الكبر والتعقيد،
a big conurbation of lots and lots of complex ideas.
مجتمع مدني به الكثير والكثير من الأفكار المعقدة.
The Italian architect Aldo Rossi,
المهندس المعماري الإيطالي ألدو روسي،
a 20th-century architect who died at the end of the last century,
وهو مهندس معماري من القرن العشرين مات بنهاية القرن الماضي،
made a very profound statement.
أدلى بتصريح عميق جدًا.
He said architecture is the making of the city over time.
قال أن العمارة هي بناء مدينة على مر الزمان.
I think that's a great statement,
أعتقد أن هذا التصريح عظيم،
because it talks, on one level, about the individual production
لأنه يتحدث على أحد المستويات عن الإنتاج الفردي
and manufacture of an object -- architecture --
وتصنيع كيان - معماري -
and it talks about architecture as being a form of cultural production,
ويتحدث عن العمارة باعتبارها شكلًا من أشكال الإنتاج الثقافي،
as something that speaks to an issue
كشيء يتحدث عن قضية
or speaks to ideas that are bigger than the sum of the parts of the building,
أو يتحدث عن أفكار أكبر من مجموع أجزاء المبنى،
and it relates it to the city.
ويربطه بالمدينة.
It also suggested that it's a constant, dynamic, changing process.
ويقترح كذلك أنها عملية حيوية متغيرة باستمرار.
And I think that's a very important thing to understand,
وأظن أن فهم هذا الأمر هام للغاية،
that it's also part of the program.
لأنه أيضًا جزء من البرنامج.
It's nothing to do with visual, it's to do with the program.
وليس له علاقة بالجزء البصري ولكنه مرتبط بالبرنامج.
It's how does this evolve, what are the dynamics,
إنه عن كيفية تطور الأمر، وماهية حركته،
what are the components, what are the elements
وطبيعة مكوناته، وعناصره
that contribute to the unraveling and the creation of the city?
التي تساهم في تكشف وتكوين المدينة؟
It also speaks to the fact that the city is something that can be imagined.
كما يتحدث عن حقيقة أن المدينة هي شيء يمكن تخيله.
In the same way as we can conceive and imagine of a space or a building,
فبنفس الطريقة التي نتصور ونتخيل بها حيزًا أو مبنى،
we can conceive and imagine of a city.
يمكننا تصور وتخيل المدينة.
And it speaks to the idea of the individual and the collective.
ويتحدث عن فكرة الفرد والجماعة.
And it's that link -- the individual to the collective,
وهذا الرابط بين الفرد والجماعة،
the idea of the civitas, the idea of the society --
وفكرة المواطنة والمجتمع،
that I think is a really important axiom
التي أعتقد أنها بديهية هامة حقًا
for understanding how design can infiltrate
لفهم كيف يمكن أن يتغلغل التصميم
and how design can effect change.
ويؤثر في التغيير.
These are some images of how Port of Spain evolved
هذه بعض الصور عن كيفية تطور (بورت أوف سبين)
over a relatively short period of 200 years,
خلال فترة قصيرة نسبيًا هي مائتي عام،
from a colonial plan that was developed following some ordinances
من مخطط استعماري تم تطويره وفقًا لمراسيم
sent out by the king of Spain,
أرسلها ملك أسبانيا،
called the Laws of the Indies.
تسمى قوانين (إنديز).
Many cities in the Caribbean and Latin America
العديد من المدن في البحر الكاريبي وأمريكا اللاتينية
were predicated and formulated on this.
أسست وشكلت وفقًا لهذا.
It was a gesture, it was a single design
لقد كانت بادرة، كان تصميمًا واحدًا
that addressed the needs and the requirements
يلبي احتياجات ومتطلبات
of those establishing cities and new colonies.
أولئك الذين ينشئون المدن والمستعمرات الجديدة.
And it expanded, and over time, as trade began to develop in Trinidad,
ثم اتسعت، ومع مرور الوقت، وتطور التجارة في (ترينداد)،
the city expanded, and it grew,
اتسعت المدينة، ونمت،
and it started appropriating, more and more, the surrounding landscape,
وبدأت بالتدريج في الاستيلاء على المساحات المحيطة،
until it grew to pretty much what we have today,
حتى انتهت إلى ما أصبحت عليه اليوم،
or what we understand to be the city of Port of Spain.
أو ما نراه مدينة (بورت أوف سبين).
But as we all know,
ولكن كما نعلم جميعًا،
that process grew also on a kind of macro scale as well.
أن هذه العملية نمت أيضًا على المستوى الكلي.
We have the evolution and the development of this big conurbation
فلدينا التنمية والتطوير لهذا التجمع السكني الكبير
that stretches from Port of Spain to the west
الممتد من (بورت أوف سبين) في الغرب
and over to Arouca in the east
وحتى (أروكا) في الشرق،
and seems to be continuing.
وما زال مستمرًا.
So we've developed into this concept or idea
لذلك فقد قمنا بالتطوير داخل هذا المبدأ
that far exceeds the original Laws of the Indies plan.
الذي تجاوز القوانين الأصلية لخطة (إنديز).
And it's turned into a complex arrangement and matrix
وقد تحولت إلى مصفوفة معقدة
of infrastructures and complex issues,
من البنيات الأساسية والقضايا المركبة،
issues that, in many ways, have led to a lot of problems.
وهي قضايا أدت إلى العديد من المشاكل في أكثر من موضع.
They've led to a lot of infrastructural problems.
فأدت إلى مشكلات عدة في البنية التحتية.
And we share this with many, many cities in the world.
ونحن نتشارك هذا الأمر مع كثير من المدن حول العالم.
Cities all over the world are expanding, they're increasing,
فالمدن حول العالم تتوسع وتزداد،
they're undergoing the same type of development that we've undergone
وتمر بنفس نوع التطور الذي مررنا به،
to the point where the original Port of Spain and the downtown Port of Spain
حتى أن مدينة (بورت أوف سبين) الأصلية ووسط مدينة (بورت أوف سبين)
that used to comprise the city, used to constitute the city,
التي اعتادت أن تشمل المدينة، وتشكلها،
has now turned into this sort of megalopolis, this sprawl,
تحولت الآن إلى هذا النوع من المدن الكبرى، هذا الامتداد،
and it's difficult to comprehend.
الذي يصعب إدراكه.
And when we think of the problems,
وعندما نفكر في المشكلات،
we think of the infrastructural problems: the water, the power,
نفكر في مشكلات البنية التحتية: مثل الماء، والطاقة،
the traffic congestion,
والازدحام المروري،
the crime, the segregation, the polarization that exists,
والجريمة، والتمييز العنصري، والاستقطاب الموجود،
the situation that has led to what's happened in this country recently
وهو الوضع الذي أدى إلى ما حدث في هذه البلاد حديثًا
with the state of emergency ...
وفرض حالة الطوارئ...
Sometimes it seems completely insurmountable.
وهو ما يبدو في بعض الأحيان مستحيلًا.
It seems like we've got to a point where we can't really control it
يبدو وكأننا وصلنا إلى وضع لا يمكننا التحكم به
in the way that we can control that original plan.
بنفس الطريقة التي تحكمنا بها في التخطيط الأصلي.
We can't really control this anymore.
لا يمكننا التحكم به بعد الآن.
It's almost as if we're victims of the city,
يبدو الأمر كما لو كنا ضحايا المدينة،
rather than people that have willingly or willfully designed the city
بدلًا من الأشخاص الذين صمموا المدينة عمدًا وطواعية
or formulated the city.
أو الذين شكلوا المدينة.
Another phenomenon that has happened commensurate with these issues
ظاهرة أخرى حدثت تتناسب مع هذه القضايا
of size and scale of infrastructure
من حجم ومقياس البنية التحتية
is the predomination of what I would call "typologies,"
هو هيمنة ما أسميه "النماذج"،
different types of development.
وهي أنواع أخرى من التطوير.
We're all familiar with the high-rise development.
جميعنا معتادون على تطوير الأبنية الشاهقة.
This is some buildings in Hong Kong,
هذه هي بعض الأبنية في هونج كونج،
you know, the magnificent, tall structures that cost a fortune to build.
كما تعلمون، الإنشاءات العالية الفخمة التي تكلف ثروة لبنائها.
But they predominate;
ولكنها تهيمن،
it's almost as if you can't have a city
كما لو أنه لن يكون لدينا مدينة
unless you've got a high-rise building in it.
إلا إن كانت تحتوي هذه الأبنية الشاهقة بها.
They're symbolic, they seem emblematic with modernity and development.
إنها رمزية، وتبدو كشعار للحداثة والتنمية.
And then shopping malls is another predominant type,
ثم مراكز التسوق، وهي نوع آخر مهيمن،
another prevalent type that all cities want to have,
نوع سائد آخر تريده جميع المدن،
the idea that you can concentrate all these shops
فكرة أنه يمكنك تركيز كل هذه المتاجر،
and all this retail activity in one place
وكل هذا النشاط التجاري في مكان واحد،
and create an environment for people to come and do specific retail functions
وإنشاء بيئة للناس ليأتوا ويمارسوا أعمالًا تجارية معينة،
and purchase things and be in a specific place at a specific time.
ويشتروا الأشياء، ويكونوا في نفس المكان في نفس الوقت.
And then the highway, the idea of cutting through landscapes
ثم الطرق السريعة، وفكرة قطع المشاهد المحيطة لإنشائها
And then we also have suburban development.
لدينا أيضًا تطوير الضواحي.
These are all typologies
وهذه جميعها نماذج رمزية
that are emblematic of the type of development that has taken place
لنوع التنمية التي تحدث في المدن الحديثة،
in modern cities, in Port of Spain and cities all over the world.
في (بورت أوف سبين) وجميع المدن حول العالم.
Now, there's nothing wrong with shopping malls,
لا يوجد شيء خاطئ في مراكز التسوق،
there's nothing wrong with highways,
أو شيء خاطئ في الطرق السريعة،
and there's nothing wrong with high-rise buildings or suburban development.
ولا يوجد شيء خاطئ في تطوير الأبنية الشاهقة والضواحي.
What is kind of wrong is that what we seem to be doing
ما هو خاطئ هو ما نفعله
is privileging types or ways of building
بتفضيل أنواع أو طرق للبناء،
or ideas about building
أو أفكار عن البناء،
above other really very important ways
أكثر من طرق أخرى شديدة الأهمية
of how we can conceive or how we imagine space.
لتصور وتخيل المساحات.
What about schools?
ماذا عن المدارس؟
What about parks?
ماذا عن المتنزهات؟
What about making streets that are really comfortable to walk on
ماذا عن إنشاء شوارع يكون المشي فيها مريحًا،
and the people are not confronting traffic noise and congestion all the time?
حيث لا يواجه الناس ضوضاء وزحامًا مروريًّا طوال الوقت؟
Where is that in the equation?
أين هذه الأشياء في المعادلة؟
It seems that with our focus on these types of structures and these typologies,
يبدو أنه بتركيزنا على هذه الأشكال الإنشائية وهذه النماذج،
which are motivated and driven primarily because they generate profit,
التي يحركها ويحفزها في المقام الأول تحقيقها للأرباح،
they're part of an economic consumer system,
وأنها جزء من نظام المستهلك الاقتصادي،
they generate profit, that's why they're favored,
فهي تحقق ربحًا، ولذلك يتم تفضيلها،
that's why they are privileged above other types of development.
ولذلك تُميز عن أشكال التطوير الأخرى.
But schools,
ولكن المدارس،
parks,
والمتنزهات،
elements of cities that used to be really significant and really important
وعناصر المدن التي لطالما كانت بالغة الأهمية
are being diminished and marginalized
يتم تقليصها وتهميشها
as a consequence of the focus on this type of development.
كنتيجة للتركيز على هذا النوع من التطوير.
They're undermining the integrity of the city,
إنها تضعف سلامة المدينة،
they're undermining the capacity of the city
وتضعف قدرة المدينة
to accommodate social interaction,
على استيعاب التفاعل الاجتماعي،
to accommodate everybody,
واستيعاب الجميع،
because the other thing is they're also exclusive.
لأنها من وجه آخر حصرية.
To work in a high-end office, you need to be qualified,
للعمل في مكتب راق لابد أن تكون مؤهلًا،
you need to be educated,
وأن تكون متعلمًا،
or you need to have access or the resources
أو أن يكون لديك الموارد والإمكانية
to get the qualifications or the training that allow you to get the job in there.
للحصول على المؤهلات والتدريب الذي يمكنك من الحصول على الوظيفة هناك.
If you don't have those, you work outside somewhere.
وإن لم تمتلك هذه المؤهلات فستعمل في مكان ما بالخارج.
We're not concerned about what those places are like,
ولا يعنينا ما تبدو عليه هذه الأماكن،
you just go and work somewhere else.
عليك فقط الذهاب للعمل بمكان آخر.
Similarly, those people that used to live in the cities
وبالمثل، الناس الذين اعتادوا على العيش في المدن
or used to live and contribute to the life of cities
أو اعتادوا على العيش والمشاركة في حياة المدن
are being pushed out because buildings like high-rise buildings push them out.
يتم دفعهم للخروج منها لأن المنشآت الشاهقة تدفعهم للخروج.
There's a premium on land price that pushes people out of cities.
فارتفاع أسعار الأراضي يدفع الناس للخروج من المدن.
People can't go to shopping malls unless they've got cars,
ولا يمكن للناس الذهاب إلى مراكز التسوق بدون سيارات،
because those malls are generally located on the peripheries of cities.
لأن هذه المراكز عادة تقع على حدود المدن.
People can't go buy things in shopping malls,
ولا يمكن للناس الشراء من مراكز التسوق،
because they don't have enough disposable income;
لأنهم لا يملكون فائضًا في الدخل،
they're not going to spend money there.
فلن ينفقوا أموالهم هناك.
So those types of buildings, whilst they work for sectors of society,
لذلك فعلى الرغم من فعالية هذه الأنواع من المنشآت لقطاع من المجتمع،
don't work for everybody.
ولكنها لا تصلح للجميع.
They're not equitable.
فهي ليست عادلة.
Yet, an undue amount of attention is paid by government, by society
ومع ذلك توجه الحكومة والمجتمع الكثير من الانتباه
on ensuring that those types of buildings proliferate,
لضمان انتشار هذه الأنواع من المنشآت،
because they're seen as positive aspects of development --
لأنها تبدو كمؤشر جيد على التنمية...
at the expense of types of building and types of program
على حساب أنواع المنشآت والبرامج
that could be beneficial to everybody,
التي قد تفيد الجميع،
types of program that encourage interaction,
وأنواع البرامج التي تشجع التفاعل،
that encourage education,
وتشجع التعليم،
that encourage people to be with each other
وتشجع الناس على أن يكونوا مع بعضهم،
and encourage a sense of community.
وتشجع الإحساس المجتمعي.
These types of development dissipate society,
هذه الأشكال من التطوير تشتت المجتمع،
they disaggregate society, they polarize society.
وتفرق المجتمع وتستقطبه.
They create isolated groups of activity
وتنشئ مجموعات منفصلة من الأنشطة
to which access depends upon how much money you've got in your pocket.
حيث تعتمد القدرة على الوصول إليها على قدر ما تملكه من مال.
It's a polarizing and negative force.
وهي قوة استقطاب سلبية.
We see it in this city,
نحن نرى ذلك في هذه المدينة،
and we're seeing it more and more other cities.
ونراه بشكل متزايد في مدن أخرى.
And what ends up happening
وما ننتهي إلى حدوثه
is that we end up with this sort of stack, that's like a time bomb.
هو هذا القدر من التراكم الذي يشبه القنبلة الموقوتة.
At some point the system must collapse, it's really not sustainable.
فهناك نقطة سينهار عندها النظام، لذلك هذا النمط ليس مستدامًا.
It's like the economic system in the world today --
يشبه ذلك النظام الاقتصادي في العالم اليوم...
it's really not a sustainable system,
فهو ليس نظامًا مستدامًا،
and we have to find ways of addressing it.
وينبغي أن نجد طرقًا لمعالجته.
Design can't provide the solution,
لا يمكن للتصميم أن يوفر الحل،
but what it can address is some of the conditions that people live with.
ولكن ما يمكنه معالجته هو بعض الظروف التي يعيش فيها الناس.
It can address some of the circumstances in which people find themselves,
يمكنه معالجة بعض الظروف التي يجد الناس أنفسهم فيها،
some of the areas of cities
وبعض المساحات في المدن
to which people have been shunted or pushed aside
حيث تم دفع الناس خارجها
because they can no longer afford to live in the center,
لأنهم لا يستطيعون تحمل تكلفة العيش في المركز.
and they can't participate actively or fully
ولا يمكنهم المشاركة بفعالية أو كليًا
in this consumerized, capitalized system.
في هذا النظام الاستهلاكي الرأسمالي.
And we need to try and conceive of how we can transform
وعلينا محاولة إدراك كيف يمكننا تحويل
these types of spaces,
هذه الأنواع من المساحات،
how we can integrate the activities that happen in these types of spaces
وكيف ندمج الأنشطة التي تحدث في هذه الأنواع من المساحات
within a bigger picture,
في صورة أشمل،
how we can identify small moves or small gestures,
وكيف نتعرف على الحركات والإيماءات الصغيرة،
whether through design or economic initiative or social initiative
سواء من خلال تصميم أو مبادرة اقتصادية أو اجتماعية،
that effect change and that allow transformation of spaces
تؤثر على التغيير وتسمح بتحويل المساحات
that encourage and facilitate greater participation.
التي تشجع وتسهل المزيد من المشاركة.
And there are lots of ways of doing that.
وهناك الكثير من الطرق لفعل ذلك.
And whilst it might seem complex when we look at cities,
وبينما قد تبدو معقدة عندما ننظر إلى المدن،
when we look at the aggregate parts of cities, it may seem insurmountable.
عندما ننظر إلى الأجزاء الكلية للمدينة سيبدو أنها لا تقهر.
But if we try and isolate individual acts, individual ways of looking at things
ولكن إن حاولنا عزل الأفعال الفردية، والطرق الفردية للنظر للأشياء،
and formulate a program, a manner or way of understanding how we can do that,
وقمنا بصياغة برنامج أو أسلوب أو طريقة لفهم كيف يمكننا القيام بذلك،
then we can get nearer to achieving or effecting
فسنقترب أكثر من تحقيق أو التأثير
some kind of social change.
على نوع من التغيير الاجتماعي.
And there are examples in the world where that's been done.
وهناك أمثلة في العالم حيث تم فعل ذلك.
Barcelona is a really good example of a city where people sat down
فمدينة برشلونة مثال جيد حيث اجتمع الناس
and collectively and actively tried to conceive of ways
وحاولوا جميعًا بفعالية تصور الطرق
in which they could effect change,
التي يمكنهم من خلالها إحداث التغيير،
and they did it very successfully.
وفعلوا ذلك بنجاح تام.
And nearer to home, in Bogotá,
وبالقرب من موطني، في (بوغوتا)،
Enrique Peñalosa, the mayor of Bogotá,
إنريكي بينالوسا، عمدة (بوغوتا)،
when he took office, he decided,
الذي قرر عندما تولى منصبه:
"I'm not going to spend billions of dollars on creating more highways.
"لن أنفق مليارات الدولارات لإنشاء المزيد من الطرق السريعة.
I'm going to appropriate the funds I have,
سأخصص التمويل المتاح
and I'm going to create places --
وسأنشئ أماكن...
parks that everybody can use, public spaces that people can use."
متنزهات متاحة للجميع، وأماكن عامة لكل الناس."
And as he created, more and more people came into those spaces.
وكلما أنشأ أماكن أكثر زاد عدد القادمين إلى هذه الأماكن.
And those spaces were very effective in encouraging participation,
وكانت هذه المساحات فعالة للغاية في التشجيع على المشاركة،
encouraging senses of community amongst people,
ودعم الحس المجتمعي بين الناس،
getting people to come together
وحث الناس على التضامن،
to forget what little trifling contests they had between each other,
ونسيان السباق العبثي الذي كان بينهم،
to start doing things together,
والبدء بفعل الأشياء معًا،
to start moving around the city together
والتنقل عبر المدينة معًا،
and try to start acting together.
والبدء في العمل معًا.
So there are ways of doing it; there are models.
يوجد طريقة لفعل ذلك، وهناك نماذج له.
And it comes back to this idea of program.
ويعود الأمر لفكرة البرنامج.
What's our program?
ما هو برنامجنا؟
Well, I think we want to create equitable society.
أعتقد أننا نرغب في إنشاء مجتمع عادل.
Then we want to create societies
ثم نرغب في إنشاء مجتمعات
where there's active and equitable participation for everybody
حيث توجد مشاركة فعالة ومنصفة للجميع
and where we can break down some of those inhibitions, those barriers.
وحيث يمكننا تحطيم هذا الكبت وهذه الحواجز.
We can remove economic stigma,
يمكننا محو الوصمة الاقتصادية،
we can remove stigma around race,
ويمكننا محو وصمة العرق،
around where you live, around all those factors
ووصمة مكان سكنك، وجميع هذه العوامل،
and try and bring people together in constructed and effective ways.
وأن نحاول جمع الناس معًا بطرق منظمة وفعالة.
In Trinidad, there are a number of examples.
هناك عدد من الأمثلة في (ترينيداد)،
There are opportunities to do this all over the place.
هناك فرص لفعل ذلك في كل مكان.
This is City Gate.
هذه هي بوابة المدينة.
It's the entrance to the city for tens of thousands of people.
إنها المدخل إلى المدينة لعشرات الآلاف من الناس.
People come in and out of it every day.
يدخل ويخرج الناس منها كل يوم.
And yet, what they're confronted with is pretty bleak, horrid, grey,
ومع ذلك، فإن ما يواجهونه هو شيء كئيب فظيع رمادي
unwelcoming and sometimes unsafe
غير مرحب وفي بعض الأحيان غير آمن
because of all the traffic zooming around.
بسبب كل حركة المرور حوله.
And that space from City Gate that moves up to Independence Square
وهذه المساحة من بوابة المدينة التي تمتد حتى ميدان الاستقلال
could be a really wonderful experience, you know, with landscaping,
يمكن أن تصبح تجربة رائعة، بتنسيق الموقع،
with proper accommodation of the sort of facilities and amenities
والتكييف المناسب لنوع المنشآت ووسائل الراحة
that people would need and would enjoy.
التي سيحتاج إليها الناس ويستمتعون بها.
It could become a really very important civic space.
يمكنها أن تصبح مساحة مدنية هامة.
This is the Prado in Havana.
هذا هو ممشى (برادو) في (هافانا).
It's just a notional idea of how that space could be treated
إنها مجرد فكرة افتراضية عن كيفية التعامل مع هذه المساحة،
so that movement in and out of the city every day
حتى تصبح الحركة من وإلى المدينة كل يوم
becomes a really important and uplifting transition
تحولًا مهمًا ونهضويًّا
from the maxi taxi to the place where you work.
من سيارة الأجرة إلى مكان عملك.
In San Fernando we've got the waterfront,
في (سان فرناندو) لدينا واجهة بحرية،
which is a really very beautiful part of this landscape in this country,
وهي جزء جميل حقًا من المشهد في هذا البلد،
but is in complete neglect.
ولكنها مهملة تمامًا.
There are some really beautiful, fine examples of 19th-century architecture
توجد أمثلة جميلة حقًا من عمارة القرن 19،
that form, in and of themselves, some really fine spaces.
والتي تشكل من نفسها مساحات جميلة حقًا.
We need to we need to look at those spaces, we need to appropriate them,
نحتاج إلى النظر إلى تلك المساحات، وإلى ملاءمتها،
we need to determine uses for those spaces
نحتاج إلى تحديد استخدامات لهذه المساحات
that would encourage all types of activity:
تشجع على جميع أنواع الأنشطة:
spaces for performance,
مساحات للتمثيل،
spaces for children to play in
ومساحات ليلعب بها الأطفال،
and learn that it's cool and it's OK and it's fun to be around other people,
ويتعلموا أنه من الرائع والمقبول والممتع تواجدهم مع أناس آخرين،
spaces for people to do all the kinds of activities that people like to do,
ومساحات للناس لممارسة جميع الأنشطة التي يحبونها،
that they enjoy doing collectively
والتي يستمتعون بفعلها جماعيًا،
and that benefit society
والتي تفيد المجتمع
and encourage people to interact,
وتشجع الناس على التفاعل
regardless of their social or economic circumstance,
بصرف النظر عن ظروفهم الاجتماعية والاقتصادية،
or places for people to reflect,
أو أماكن للناس للتفكير،
parks, places for people to sit and relax.
ومتنزهات وأماكن للناس ليجلسوا ويسترخوا.
And there are lots of ways we can do that,
وهناك طرق عديدة تمكننا من فعل ذلك،
ways in which we can address and look at how we break down those barriers.
طرق يمكننا من خلالها معالجة وإلقاء نظرة على كيفية كسر هذه الحواجز.
We can do it with architectural language.
يمكننا فعل ذلك بلغة معمارية.
We can look at the ways that spaces are formulated
يمكننا النظر إلى الطرق التي تتشكل بها المساحات
to break down divisions and barriers between inside and outside,
لكسر الانقسامات والحواجز بين الداخل والخارج،
between green and hard surfaces
وبين المسطحات الخضراء والصلبة،
and try and generate spaces that really encourage interaction,
ومحاولة إنشاء مساحات تشجع على التفاعل،
encourage people to do things together
وتشجع الناس على فعل الأشياء معًا،
and encourage a sense of community.
وتشجع الحس المجتمعي.
We need to mandate government,
نحن بحاجة إلى تفويض الحكومة،
we need to provide examples to developers, to people
نحتاج إلى توفير أمثلة للمطورين وللناس،
to generate that the benefit of these may not be measured
لترسيخ أن فائدة هذا الأمر ربما لا تقاس
in a financial return on investment,
بالعائد المادي للاستثمار،
but the social benefit to us all is really immeasurable in the long run.
ولكن العائد الاجتماعي لنا جميعًا لا حصر له على المدى الطويل.
And if we do that, I think we can demonstrate --
وإذا فعلنا ذلك، أعتقد أنه يمكننا أن نبين...
and we've demonstrated in the past that designers had the capacity to do that --
وقد بيننا في الماضي أن المصممين لديهم القدرة على فعل ذلك...
I think if we can do that, we can demonstrate to people
أعتقد أنه إن أمكننا فعل ذلك، فسنبين للناس
that society is an inclusive community,
أن المجتمع هو تجمع شامل،
and that if everybody is included,
وأنه إذا تم تضمين الجميع،
and if everybody feels part of the society,
وإذا كان الجميع يشعرون بأنهم جزء من المجتمع،
then we have a much better chance of ensuring a sustainable future.
فستكون لدينا فرصة أفضل لضمان مستقبل مستدام.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.